<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Committee Report Investigating Doctor Robert Knox</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <!-- This is where you put information about the digital edition you're creating -->
                <publisher>Marry Ann Orfanos</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boston College</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <p>Educational Use Permitted: This Item is protected by copyright and/or related
                        rights. You are free to use this Item in any way that is permitted by the
                        copyright and related rights legislation that applies to your use. In
                        addition, no permission is required from the rights-holder(s) for
                        educational uses. For other uses, you need to obtain permission from the
                        rights-holder(s).</p>
                    <p>https://rightsstatements.org/page/InC-EDU/1.0/?language=en</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- This is where you put information about the source you're digitizing -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>Report of the Committee</title>
                    <author> Need to determine </author>
                    <!-- Unsure how to designate several authors -->
                    <publisher>Caledonian Mercury</publisher>
                    <date when="1829-03-13">March 13, 1829</date>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">No. 16,782</biblScope>
                    <!-- mention in website at the very end of the issue -->
                    <note>Digital Access available on Gale's <hi rend="italic">British Library
                            Newspapers</hi></note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- This is an optional element where you should put information about the encoding choices you made -->
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The committee report is provided here to reflect the submission of the original
                    document alongside Knox's letter to the editor Caledonian Mercury.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> Much of these annotations provide evidence, context, or biographical
                    clarification that better informs the reader as to the historical circumstances
                    and complexities of this event.
                    <!-- Should I make this second sentence a web page feature instead? Might be too detailed for this purpose -->
                    Henry Lonsdale's well-known biographical account and collection of Knox's
                    writings represents this letter the same way with the intent to use the
                    committee report to further validate Knox's exoneration with official
                    documentation, and this annotated incorporation of the same material is an
                    attempt complicate this oversimplification.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl/>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <!-- This is an optional element where you can put non-bibliographic (usually contextual) information about the source you're digitizing -->
            <creation><date/></creation>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- This is where you keep track of the changes you make to your file -->
            <change who="Marry Ann" when="2024-04-02"> Cleaned up the file metadata, making
                finishing touches/preparations</change>
            <change who="Marry Ann" when="2024-03-29"> Added footnotes</change>
            <change who="Marry Ann" when="2024-03-27"> Added closer signatures and date, added
                horbars, added postscript</change>
            <change who="Marry Ann" when="2024-03-20"> Created file, metadata, and added
                transcription. Need some help with select features.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1>
                <milestone unit="undefined" rend="horbar-short"/>
                <div2 type="report">
                    <opener> Report of the Committee<ref target="#n01"/>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Committee who, at the request of Dr.Knox, undertook to investigate the
                        truth or falsehood of the rumours in circulation regarding him, have gone
                        into an extensive examination of evidence, in the course of which they have
                        courted information from every quarter. They have been readily furnished
                        with all which they required from Dr.Knox himself; and though they have
                        failed in some attempts to procure evidence, they have in most quarters
                        succeeded in obtaining it, and especially from those persons who have been
                        represented to them as having spoken the most confidently in support of
                        these rumours ; and they have unanimously agreed on the following report
                        :--</p>
                    <p>1. The Committee have seen no evidence that Dr. Knox or his assistants knew
                        that murder was committed in procuring any of the subjects brought to his
                        rooms, and the Committee firmly believe that they did not.</p>
                    <p> 2. On the question whether any suspicion of murder at any time existed in
                        Dr.Knox’s mind, the Committee would observe that there were certainly
                        several circumstances (already known to the public), regarding some of the
                        subjects brought by Burke and Hare, which, now that the truth has come out,
                        appear calculated to excite that suspicion, particularly the very early
                        period after death at which they were brought to the rooms, and the absence
                        of external marks of disease, together with the opinion previously expressed
                        by Dr. Knox, in common with most other anatomists, of the generally
                        abandoned character of persons engaged in this traffic. But, on the other
                        hand, the Committee, after much anxious inquiry, have found no evidence of
                        their actually having excited it in the mind of Dr.Knox, or of any other of
                        the individuals who saw the bodies of these unfortunate persons prior to the
                        apprehension of Burke.</p>
                    <p> The bodies do not appear in any instance to have borne any external marks by
                        which it could have been known whether they had died by violence or suddenly
                        from natural causes, or from diseases of short duration ; and the mode of
                        protracted anatomical dissection practised in this and other similar
                        establishments, is such as would have made it very difficult to ascertain
                        the causes of death, even if special inquiry had been instituted with that
                        intention. </p>
                    <p> No evidence whatever has come before the Committee that any suspicion of
                        murder was expressed to Dr.Knox by any one, either of his assistants or of
                        his very numerous class (amounting upwards of 400 students), or other
                        persons who were in the practice of frequently visiting his rooms ; and
                        there are several circumstances in his conduct, particularly the complete
                        publicity with which his establishment was managed, and his anxiety to lay
                        each subject before the students as soon as possible after its reception,
                        which seem to the Committee strongly to indicate that he had no suspicion of
                        the atrocious means by which they had been procured.</p>
                    <p> It has also been proved to the satisfaction of the Committee, that no
                        mutilation or disfigurement of any kind was ever practised with a view to
                        conceal the features, or abstract unseasonably any part of the body, the
                        presence of which might have facilitated detection ; and it appears clearly
                        that the subjects brought by Burke and Hare were dissected in the same
                        protracted manner as those procured from any other quarter.<ref
                            target="#n02"/></p>
                    <p> 3. The Committee have thought it proper to inquire further, whether there
                        was anything faulty or negligent in the regulations under which subjects
                        were received into Dr.Knox’s rooms, which gave or might give a peculiar
                        facility to the disposal of the bodies obtained by these crimes ; and on
                        this point they think it their duty to state their opinion fully.</p>
                    <p> It appears in evidence, that Dr. Knox had formed and expressed the opinion,
                        long prior to any dealings with Burke and Hare, that a considerable supply
                        of subjects for anatomical purposes might be procured by purchase, and
                        without any crime, from the relations or connections of deceased persons in
                        the lowest ranks of society. </p>
                    <p> In forming this opinion, whether mistaken or not, the Committee cannot
                        consider Dr. Knox to have been culpable. They believe there is nothing
                        contrary to the law of the land in procuring subjects for dissection in that
                        way ; and they know that the opinion which Dr.Knox had formed on this point,
                        though never acted on to any extent in this country, has been avowed by
                        others of the highest character in the profession. But they think that Dr.
                        Knox acted on this opinion in a very incautious manner. </p>
                    <p> This preconceived opinion seems to have led him to give a ready ear to the
                        plausible stories of Burke, who appears from all the evidence before the
                        Committee to have conducted himself with great address and appearance of
                        honesty, as well in his conversation with Dr.Knox, as in his more frequent
                        intercourse with his assistants ; and always to have represented himself as
                        engaged in negotiations of that description, and occasionally to have asked
                        and obtained money in advance to enable him and his associate to conclude
                        bargains. </p>
                    <p> Unfortunately also Dr.Knox had been led, apparently in consequence of the
                        extent and variety of his avocations, to entrust the dealings with persons
                        supplying subjects, and the reception of the subjects brought, to his
                        assistants (seven in number) and to his doorkeeper indiscriminately. It
                        appears also that he directed or allowed these dealings to be conducted on
                        the understanding (common to him with some other anatomists) that it would
                        only tend to diminish or delivery the supply of subjects to make any
                        particular inquiry of the persons bringing them as to the place and mode of
                        obtaining them. </p>
                    <p>In these respects the Committee consider the practice which was then adopted
                        in Dr.Knox’s rooms (whatever be the usage in this or other establishments in
                        regard to subjects obtained in the ordinary way) to have been very improper
                        in the case of persons bringing bodies which had not been interred. They
                        think that the notoriously bad character of persons who generally engage in
                        in any such traffic, in addition to the novelty and particular nature of the
                        system on which these men professed to be acting, undoubtedly demanded
                        greater vigilance. </p>
                    <p>The extent, therefore, to which (judging from the evidence which they have
                        been able to procure) the Committee think that Dr.Knox can be blamed on
                        account of transactions with Burke and Hare is, that by this laxity of the
                        regulations under which bodies were received into his rooms, he
                        unintentionally gave a degree of facility to the disposal of the victims of
                        their crimes, which under better regulations would not have existed<ref
                            target="#n03"/>, and which is doubtless matter of deep and lasting
                        regret, not only to himself, but to all who have reflected on the importance
                        and are therefore interested in the prosecution of the study of anatomy. But
                        while they point out this circumstance as the only ground of censure which
                        they can perhaps discover in the conduct of Dr.Knox, it is fair to observe
                        that perhaps the recent disclosures have made it appear reprehensible to
                        many who would not otherwise have adverted to its possible consequences. </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>John Robinson <hi rend="italic">(Chairman).</hi></signed>
                        <signed>W.P.Alison.</signed>
                        <signed>Geo Ballingall.</signed>
                        <signed>M.P.Brown.</signed>
                        <signed>George Sinclair.</signed>
                        <signed>James Russell.</signed>
                        <signed>W. Hamilton.</signed>
                        <signed>J. Shaw Stewart.</signed>
                        <signed>Thomas Allan.</signed>
                        <date when="1829-03-13">13th March 1829</date>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <milestone unit="undefined" rend="horbar-short"/>
                <!-- could get more itemized about the size with unit, but since we're using HTML, will be relegated to that instead -->
                <postscript>
                    <!-- Lonsdale version different from the original; removed "For the information of our country readers, we may add the designations of" -->
                    <p>
                        <ref target="#n04"/>For the information of our country readers, we may add
                        the designations of the gentlemen who formed the Committee were Mr. Robinson
                        (afterwards Sir John), Secretary to the Royal Society ; Mr. Brown, Advocate
                        ; Mr. Russell, Professor of Clinical Surgery ; Mr. Stewart, Advocate ; Dr.
                        Alison, Professor of the Theory of Physic ; Sir Geo. Ballinghall, Professor
                        of Military Surgery ; Mr. Sinclair the younger (or Sir George), of Ulbster ;
                        Sir W. Hamilton, Bart., Professor of Universal History ; Mr. Allan, banker,
                        in Edinburgh.</p>
                    <!-- Postscript element exists for a reason -->
                </postscript>
            </div1>
            <note type="editorial" xml:id="n01"> Most if not everyone was aware that the lay
                committee which had decided Knox’s innocence was not adequate or just; the evidence
                they used to justify their decision was never once made public. An official inquiry
                and assessment of the facts of this case had been expected, but never came to pass
                (Richardson 137).</note>
            <note type="editorial" xml:id="n02"> To the contrary, there were numerous of signs of
                his and his staff’s active complicity and indiscretion. Burke said in his official
                confession that “Knox was present on two occasions when Burke and Hare delivered
                murdered bodies, and that in one case he had approved of a corpse’s freshness, but
                asked no questions” (Richardson 135). Several bodies brought to Knox were delivered
                with “blood at the mouth, nose or ears.” Daft Jamie’s head and feet were cut off in
                a likely attempt to prevent people from recognizing such a public figure in the
                dissection room, suggesting Knox was seeking to avoid accusations of foul play
                (136). Knox instructed his own staff to receive bodies without asking any
                questions.</note>
            <note type="editorial" xml:id="n03"> The committee's prescient observation here signals
                the way in which Knox's involvement in the Burke and Hare murders would become a
                central justification for passing the Anatomy Act of 1832. In order to maintain the
                status quo of corpse commodification necessary to support surgical science and avoid
                any more legal liabilities, this law would allow any dead bodies found in workhouses
                (and a number of other locations largely populated by the poor) that were not
                claimed within 48 hours to be subject to medical experimentation. Following this
                legislation was a protracted increase in the burning of any buildings housing
                practising surgeons.</note>
            <note type="editorial" xml:id="n04"> In Henry Lonsdale's collection of Knox's writings,
                his depiction of the letter and committee report do not exactly match what was
                published in the Calidonian Mercury newspaper. Lonsdale omits the phrase "For the
                information of our country readers, we may add the designations of" before the names
                of the people in the committee are listed. This is a significant choice and change,
                as there are many tonal indicators that both the writers at the Calidonian Mercury
                and much of the audience who read the newspaper were not of any inclination to
                believe Knox's attempts to shake off culpability (not the least of which being
                published on the final page of the issue). In the newspaper, the implication is that
                the people reading should know how illegitimate those passing judgment were, in
                Lonsdale's depiction it seems as though Knox or Lonsdale offered the clarification
                of who comprised the committee as an attempt at transparency (Lonsdale 88).</note>
            <!-- maybe add some more about how legislation impacted the committee's decision more than the truth of the situation -->
        </body>
    </text>



</TEI>
